Let's take a couple of minutes and talk to you about pruning trees.
It's unfortunately but trees get old, trees get sick.
Sometimes you just need a little bit more light in an area than you're currently getting and taking some branches off the bottom is a good way to handle that.
Now some jobs are going to be a little too big for you to handle, but there are a lot of jobs that with the right tools you're going to be able to do the pruning on all yourself and in this case we've got one of those jobs.
We've got a branch here down on the bottom and because of the way its been handled by other people over the course of the years, its not in very good shape.
You can see over here, somebody went and put a swing on this branch and they didn't do it the right way.
They didn't protect the branch, they put chains on there and it's cut into the branch, making the branch unhealthy and killing it.
So we've got to take it down.
What we're going to do is we're going to start by pruning the ends off the branch.
This is going to do a couple of things for us, it's going to make sure one; that I'm not dropping the branch down into a garden or existing structures and two; it's going to take some of the weight off the branch and make it safer and easier to take down.
One of the tools that everybody that has a tree in their yard should have is a pole pruner.
A pole pruner comes in a couple of different parts, one; there's a saw blade, usually detachable, we'll talk more about that in a minute.
The part that we're going to use now is a bypass pruner, operates on a pulley system that can be operated on a long string pulled from the ground.
We're going to use that right now to help take some weight off the branch.
The next thing we're going to do is start sawing parts off this.
Now by bringing it down in sections, I'm making sure it's coming down in smaller more manageable chunks that are a lot less likely to damage to me or my garden.